Guide to the Henry Dunster Baker Papers, 1794-1953
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Henry Dunster Baker papers 1794-1953
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Baker, Henry Dunster, 1873-1939.
3.0 Linear Feet 280 Items
U.S. consul official and newspaper editor and publisher.
Correspondence, scrapbooks, clippings, pamphlets, pictures, and genealogy, reflecting Baker's consular career and the Baker, Dunster, Griffiths, Speir, and Willis families of the U. S., Great Britain, and Australia. The papers relate to family affairs, Baker's work as consul (1907-1911) in Tasmania, as commercial attache in Russia during World War I, and as an opponent of trade with Russia (1930-1931). Includes some clippings and pictures (1916-1927) from the Trinidad consulate.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Henry Dunster Baker Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1970.
Biographical Note
U.S. consul official and newspaper editor and publisher.
Collection Overview
Papers of Henry D. Baker (1873-1939), U.S. consular official and newspaper editor and publisher, contain correspondence, clippings, genealogy, printed material, pictures, and volumes. The bulk of the papers before 1900 refer to the Griffiths, Speir, Willis and Austin families of England and Australia, related through Baker's wife, Gwyneth Griffiths. They concern family matters, and the service of Charles Ralph Griffiths (1790-1850) as British vice consul and consul at Buenos Aires, 1823-1846. Material after 1900 relates to the consular career of Henry Baker in Tasmania, 1907-1911, Bombay, 1913-1914, and Trinidad, 1916-1927; Baker's service as commercial attache at Petrograd, Russia; and his opposition to trade with Russia, 1930-1931. Tasmanian Scrapbook, 1907-1911, includes clippings, photographs, and pictures relating to Tasmania, Australia, New Zealand, and the islands of the Bass Straits. Scrapbook, 1911-1933, contains pamphlets, articles, speeches, pictures, clippings and letters concerning relations with Russia during World War I and in 1930-1931, and Baker's activities in the United States, Trinidad, Tasmania, India, and New Zealand. There are also printed copies of books by Baker and by Charles H. Baker; family photographs and copies of portraits, especially from the Griffiths family; photographs of Trinidad and Baker's trip to Persia, 1916; and photographs of "Erryd," Victorian home of the Griffiths in Wales. Printed material consists of speeches, articles and pamphlets by and about Baker. The clippings, 1910-1951, include articles by and about Baker and items about the countries in which he served. An extensive genealogical folder contains information about the Baker and Dunster families of America and the Griffiths, Speir, Willis, Hart, and Blondeau families of England and Australia.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Baker family
Dunster family
Griffith family
Spears family
Willis family
United States -- Foreign Office
United States -- Foreign relations -- Soviet Union
United States -- Foreign relations -- Australia
United States -- Commerce -- Soviet Union
Scrapbooks
Contents of Collection
- Papers, 1794-1953 and undated, (5 boxes)
  - Printed volumes (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 2)
  - Genealogy
  - Pictures
  - Printed materials, 1896-1951
  - Scrapbook, 1911-1933 (Box 3)
  - Frederick Griffiths' passport
  - Tasmanian scrapbook, 1907-1911 (Box 4)
  - Papers, 1794-1953 and undated (Box 5)